<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A health to the King, or, An astrological prediction of Charls II his coming to the crown of England &amp;c. / by Timothy Gadbury ...</title>
            <author>Gadbury, Timothy.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40873</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19525787</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19525787</idno>
            <idno type="VID">108981</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41372)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 108981)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1688:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A health to the King, or, An astrological prediction of Charls II his coming to the crown of England &amp;c. / by Timothy Gadbury ...</title>
                  <author>Gadbury, Timothy.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Gilbertson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Illustrated t.p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:108981:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:108981:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Health to the KING OR AN Aſtrological Prediction OF CHARLS II. HIS Coming to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By <hi>TIMOTHY GADB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY,</hi> Philomath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tempora mutantur &amp; nos mutamur in illis.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of Charles II's head</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Gilbertſon</hi> at the Bible in Guilt-ſpur-ſtreet, without Newgate. 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="owners_bookplate">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Prince of Wales's bookplate</figDesc>
                  <p>C P</p>
                  <p>ICH DI EN</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:108981:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:108981:2"/>
            <head>A Health TO THE KING</head>
            <p>THe times we live in producing altogether varieties in mens fancies, that men were ſeldom fixed to any one ſetled opinion in any thing, ſo that, <hi>Quot homines, tot ſententiae,</hi> might very well have been taken for a common Proverb in our dayes: for mens mindes changed oftener then the Moon; theſe changes were not alone in private Perſons, but among thoſe that took upon them to ſteer the Helm of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment here alſo; ſo that very few had that bleſſing among them which the Prophet <hi>David</hi> mentions, <hi>of being of one minde in a houſe;</hi> ſo that our Nation was in a condition like a man troubled with a <hi>Hectick</hi> feaver and a <hi>frency</hi> to boot, that moſt men were unſetled in the way they lived in; <hi>One man cries out for a King, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no King;</hi> and ſeeing this confuſion among us, I took into ſerious conſideration whether the King were likely to come among us or not; for though people be never ſo mad in their wayes, let them but conſider ſeriouſly, and they may ſee that a Prince may better live without a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then a people without a Prince; And though many have had opinion that he would never
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:108981:3"/>come to his Crown here in <hi>England,</hi> nay, ſome Artiſts too, as well as vulgar perſons; I ſhall here make it plain from rules of art, that he will come, though he ſhould have a multitude of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers; I pray God he may be ſetled in peace without bloodſhed, for if we ſuffer him not to come in peace, and legal terms, Forrainers will aſſiſt him, and then our condition will be the worſe; I ſhall add a line or two of an ancient pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy concerning the Kings coming in this year 1660.</p>
            <l>
               <hi>The Moon eclips'd till ſixty year,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Shall then break out and ſhine moſt clear,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>While</hi> England <hi>then for joy ſhall ſing,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>And bleſs the reigns of her good KING.</hi>
            </l>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>astrological diagram</figDesc>
               <head>The Figure of his Nativity follows.</head>
               <p>Prince <hi>Charles</hi> born 1630. <hi>May</hi> 29. 10th. 21. Ae.M.</p>
            </figure>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:108981:3"/>
            <p>In paſſing judgement of this Princely Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I ſhall not obtrude my ſingle and private opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion upon the world for Authentick, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Authority, and that of the beſt and moſt credible Aſtrologers; viz. <hi>Haly, Orignus, Guido, Banalus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I ſhall firſt ſhew ſome reaſons of our Kings un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunacy of late years.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly of his being eſtabliſhed in his Fathers Throne.</p>
            <p>And thirdly his time to continue, <hi>ad termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num vitae.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>Sect. <hi>1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHoſoever hath the Lord of the Aſcendant combuſt of the Sun ſhall ſuffer many af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions in his life time; this is verified in this Princely geniture to the knowledge of moſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the ☉ (which afflicts ☿ here) is Lord of the 12th Houſe; which ſignifies Enemies; but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as much as ☿ diſpoſes of the ☉, it notes the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to overcome at laſt; Another reaſon is, ♌ in the 4th Houſe, which ſignifies much labour and ſorrow to the Native, a confuſion and waſte of his Patrimony, loſs in Lands, Buildings, and all kinde of Edifices, trouble and anxiety in the life of his Anceſtors, loſs of eſtimation, of credit; how this hath been fulfilled on this Princely Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, let the world judge: I might here ſhew ſome reaſons why his afflictions ſhould be in his younger years, but I paſs that by, and come to,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>Sect. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">THat he ſhall be eſtabliſhed in his Fathers Throne.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maj.</hi> That perſon that hath the Lord of his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:108981:4"/>Aſcendant ſtrong in the mid-heaven, and the Sun and ♌ there alſo (if it be any Princely geniture) ſhall obtain his Fathers Kingdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Min.</hi> But this Princely Native hath the Lord of the Aſcendant ſtrong in the mid-Heaven, (or tenth Houſe) and ☉ and ♌ there alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Concl. Ergo,</hi> This Princely Native ſhall obtain his Fathers Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The major here I ſhall ſupport and ſtrengthen by ſeveral teſtimonies; Firſt, <hi>Si quando Dominus Aſcendentis fuerit, in ſigno M.C. &amp; illud ſignum fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit domus vel exaltio aut terminus vel triplicitas ejus,</hi> Haly <hi>de jud. Aſt. fol.</hi> 227. when the Lord of the Aſcendant ſhall be in the tenth Houſe, in his own dignities, and in a maſculine ſign, the Native ſhall be a King or ruler over many. Secondly, <hi>Si quando Sol fuerit in M.C. exiſtente in ſuamet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, aut in ſigno maſculino natus erit Rex, aut De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus multae gentis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Haly, pag.</hi> 5. <hi>fol.</hi> 249. <hi>Sol</hi> in the tenth Houſe gives great glory, authority, honor and dignity from Emperors, Kings, Princes, and great Perſons; he ſhall obtain the love and friendſhip of ſome eminent perſon or perſons, that ſhall exalt him from his low, unto a very high degree, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> to his Kingdom. This will be fully verified by other Nations aſſiſting him to bring him in, if we ſuffer him not to come in peace. Thirdly, If the ♌ be in the tenth Houſe happily poſited, it denotes honor and preferment to the Native, be his condition what it will; all theſe Aphoriſms agreeing, who can ſay that <hi>Carolus</hi> the Second ſhall be hindred from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Throne?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:108981:4"/>
               <head>Sect. <hi>3.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">THat his Honor and Dominion once obtained ſhall remain and endure <hi>ad terminum vitae,</hi> to the end of his Natural life.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maj.</hi> Whoſoever hath the cuſpe of honor and Dominion in his Nativity fixed, and the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficator fixed alſo in his own dignities, his honor and renown once obtained, muſt continue to the end of his life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Min.</hi> But it is thus in this Princely geniture:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> His honor, once obtained, ſhall and muſt continue to the end of his life.</p>
               <p>I need not rake over many vetuſtious forms of obſolete Authors, for the proof of this ſo conſpicuous a truth; for every Aſtrologer (let him be of never ſo ſhort a time ſtudious there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) muſt ſet his ſeal to the certainty thereof; however, to confirm this truth, hear what <hi>Origa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ſaith, <hi>fol.</hi> 703. in his Diſcourſe <hi>de duratione honorum,</hi> proving the truth of this propoſition in theſe words, <hi>Primo enim beneficus ſignificatur, ac fortis ratione eſſentialium dignitatum; ſtatum hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non, ſolum cum facilitate quadam per totam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam nati duraturum eſſe,</hi> &amp;c. The ſame doth the learned <hi>Leovitius</hi> ſay in his Ephemerides; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the ingenious <hi>Argol Ptol. par. lib.</hi> 2. ſaith, If the ſignificator of honor and dignity be in ſignes, the joy or delight in the honor and dignity will continue. We admit (by reaſon of the poſition of <hi>Caput Algol in decima domo</hi>) that this Heroick King may by a Phanatick brood, at ſometimes be diſturbed; but this can never riſe ſo high (he being once poſſeſſed) as to detriment him in the least
<pb facs="tcp:108981:5"/> in point of his Soveraignity: Neither let any man obje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to me the whimſical judgements, and Phanatiſms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Purblinde Artiſts, who out of diſaffection to this Ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> Perſon, and for a peniary reward, have canted his dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fall, and abſolute impoſſibility of ever regaining or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing his Fathers dignity: For, it is as certain, as wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is moſt certain, that this Princely Perſon ſhall recover his Fathers Glory, and his own former Illuſtrious Eſtate and Grandure, Maugre the moſt malicious Enemie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that Earth it ſelf can produce. The Stars proclaim his <hi>acceſſum ad Dominum,</hi> and from thence I predict it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the Gentry and Comonalty of <hi>England,</hi> I dedic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and ſend it, and am not aſhamed by name to own it, and therefore ſubſcribe unto it,</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my houſe on <hi>Wappin</hi> wall, righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e golden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <date>Dated <hi>April</hi> 25. 1666.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Timothy Gadbury</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Know that many will object and ſay, why did not I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forth this ſooner, but ſtayed ſo long till moſt people were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> expectation of his coming.</p>
            <p>For Anſwer hereto, had I publiſhed this ſooner I might have prejudiced the King and my ſelf too.</p>
            <p>Firſt, For had his Enemies known of his coming they miſt have ſtrengthened their hand againſt him, that his acceſſ might have been the harder before he could have ſetled here.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Powers of late we lived under were ſo ridged againſt him, that a man durſt not ſpeak his minde, much leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> write in publick; for one might with more ſafety call a H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> heard-boy King or Prince, then to call him by either of thoſe Epithites pertaining to him; and this may ſuffice any ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal man in anſwer to that Objection.</p>
            <l>
               <hi>The Kings a coming, and we all ſhall ſee</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Good days approaching, with much mirth and glee:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>The Nation ſhall rejoyce; and peace with</hi> Spain</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Shall be concluded with them once again;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Our trade i'th Nation, likewiſe ſhall increaſe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>And we enjoy proſperity and Peace:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Then our three Nations with much joy ſhall ſing,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>And paiſe the Lord for th'Raign of our good King.</hi>
            </l>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
